hello and welcome it is April 26th
2024 and we're in active inference art
stream 1.1 starting a new art related
series very appropriately with some
great art discussions and presentations
this is going to be order and change in
art with opo frascaroli presenting and
also with sander Vander croise and axel
constant here for discussion so thank
you all for joining looking forward to
the presentation and
discussion thank you Daniel thank you
everyone for for being here uh it's
great to be able to present uh to such a
knowledgeable audience of active
inference offici others and the work
that we'll be presenting today uh is a
work that Sander van uh car and myself
did a few months ago and it is a work on
a topic which I would say it's rather
neglected or marginal so far in the
active inference literature but uh as I
will try to show it is a topic that uh
is very promising it has a lot of
interesting implications and indeed in
recent years has been Gathering a lot of
attention so let's jump straight into
the topic and our starting point is uh
the REM remarkable convergence of
interest and results that has been
emerging in the last few years between
Scholars interested in the in mind and
brain from a predictive processing or
active inference perspectiv and Scholar
interested in studying the Arts and
Aesthetics from a variety of
perspectives philosophy psychology
Neuroscience but also increasingly the
history of arts and artistic practice as
well so this convergence of interests
and results is fostering an ambitious
research program that is proving
beneficial for both sides because on the
one hand predictive processing and
active inferences are increasingly seen
as uh Frameworks that can illuminate
important aspects of our aesthetic
encounters and our aesthetic experiences
while on the other hand the Arts and
Aesthetics seen from these predictive
processing or active inference
perspectives are increasingly seen as
potential Windows into important aspects
of our mental functioning so the talk
will be exploring these two directions
of
research and most of what I will say uh
is taken from these two papers uh one
that uh sand van uh car Frist and myself
wrote and that gives the title to this
presentation and the other that uh I
wrote together with s Helmut and El
Helmut Le Anda brao and both papers can
be found in this uh recently published
uh theme issue of philosophical
transactions of the Royal Society B
which is devoted entirely to these
intersections between predic processing
and active inference on the one hand and
the Arts and Aesthetics on the other
hand so if you want a sort of a uh
overview of the State ofth art on the
topic I definitely recommend checking
out this theme
issue uh the plan for the talk uh will
be pretty straightforward as I said we
will be exploring these two main
directions of current research uh the
first pertains to the ways in which we
can illuminate aspects of aesthetic
experience using the active inference
and uh in this context we will be seeing
what we mean by aesthetic experience uh
we'll be introducing the notion of sense
making and epistemic hearts uh from this
an active inference perspective and we
will be talking about how these Notions
can clarify certain aspects of our
engagement with the Arts and our
aesthetic
experiences in the second part of the
talk I will be uh we'll be talking about
ways in which on the other hand our
mental functioning can be
illuminated uh by the Arts and
Aesthetics considered from this active
inference or predictive processing
perspective and we be uh examining a
sort of analogy between what artists do
and what cognitive scientists do when
they study the mind and we will be
clarifying how an an examination of the
Arts and Aesthetics can throw light on
on among other things the Dynamics of
inference the Dynamics of affect and
certain aspects of wellbeing in
Psychopathology and in the end I will be
presenting some conclusions and some
directions for future research as well
so let's start by saying something on
how we can illuminate aesthetic
experience from an active inference
perspective now we should probably start
by clarifying what's what is our
explanatory Target here uh
that is aesthetic experiences aesthetic
experiences have been uh uh
characterized by the philosophical and
the psychological literature as
experiences traditionally associated
with the notion of beauty the perception
of beauty in some sensory array and
these are experiences that we undergo
with varying degrees of intensity in the
most varied circumstances of our life it
could be that we are uh um looking at a
wonderful Vista that we are examining
uh and finding pleasure in the
arrangement of furnitures in a living
room but most Pro most uh
characteristically aesthetic experiences
are uh uh experiences that we undergo
while engaging with art while listening
to Great pieces of music while
confronted with great uh uh work of of
visual art while reading uh great novels
and so
on now there is a set of features that
are recurrently attributed to aesthetic
experience is and that's the feature
these are the feature that we uh we are
trying to explain from this active
inference perspective uh first of all um
aesthetic experiences are considered to
be pleasurable these are experiences
that uh are accompanied by the pleasant
effective response normally this doesn't
mean that they are not uncomfortable or
uh ridle with difficulty uh but in the
end overall they tend to be pleasurable
uh they are also self self- sustaining
and with this by this I mean that uh uh
they are experiences in which we seem to
engage without any further purpose and
in which we seem to engage uh in a
continuous manner finding in this
particular sensory array that we are
examining uh noal things to examine and
to be interested in and to uh care about
as we go along and so they sustain our
serious and attention
uh throughout and they uh we seem to
care about them with without any further
utilitarian purpose in
mind um aesthetic experiences are all
often say to be
transformative uh in the sense that when
we when the painting is behind us the
music is over when we put down the book
or leave the theater we feel that we are
not the same uh as before that we have
kind changeed it and usually Chang
changeed it for the best
this
uh this is a particularly strong trait
associated with aesthetic experience
that many uh many refer to and it can
happen it can happen of course with
various degrees of intensity it could be
that you just felt like your world view
has changed slightly or it could lead to
massive Revelations
about anything basically um aesthetic
experiences are also said to be
subjective in the sense that what is
aesthetically appealing or pleasurable
to me may not aesthetic be aesthetically
appealing or pleasurable uh to you they
are also said to be transient and
evolving in the sense that they are
characterized by an evolving uh um
effective and cognitive profile that
culminates normally with a pleasurable
response but it's not that pleasurable
response or judgment alone and they also
evolving in the sense that what what I
tend to prefer
uh could change for me uh in time uh
it's not just that what you prefer and
what I prefer are different but also
what I prefer In This Moment In Time can
be different from what I prefer in
another moment in time and also uh
aesthetic experiences are tend tend to
be seen as related in some way with uh
uh feeling of freedom from existing
constraints in our perceptual cognitive
or motor process processes and a feeling
of enhanced uh perception of our
possibilities for Action we will see we
will say more about that but these are
more or less the features uh that we are
we choose to concentrate on and they are
more characteristic of of aesthetic
experiences now uh the way in which we
go about trying to explain these
characteristics uh is uh by introducing
these two Notions and trying the notion
of sense making and epistemic ARs and
trying to characterize them from an
active infant perspectives so to
understand them let's start with an
example youve probably seen pictures
like these before they are quite uh
common in the psychological literature
but perhaps you haven't seen this
particular picture before if you haven't
it would probably look like a random
array of white and black Patches at the
at the beginning but if you concentrate
enough on on it after a while you may
start to not is that there is an animal
in the picture most specifically a cow
if you can see the cow here are some
cues in the picture you just see the
face of the cow uh these are the
nostrils of the cow these are the eyes
these are the ears of the
cow now if you see the cow now you did
something pretty remarkable already in
the sense that you have arranged what
seem to be like a random array of
sensory stimulations into something
meaningful and that's what we mean by
sense making and we can like sort of
break down this process uh from an
active inference perspective by thinking
about a sort of epistemic Arc involved
in the discovery of structure in our
sensory stimulation we start with
uncertainty uncertainty about the
potential causes of of our sensory
stimulations
um these uncertainty in some cases in
this case for example um
triggers an expectation of the
possibility to reduce such uncertainty
and that's what curiosity looks like
from an active inference perspective
according to an increasing literature
there is curiosity the feeling that that
we can find structure in our sensorium
that if we look uh uh for enough time we
will be able to understand something is
uh characterized from an active
inference perspective uh as expected
uncertainty r uction or expected
Information Gain um which means the
extent to which we uh we predicted we
will be able to reduce uncertainty about
the sensory the cause the causes of our
sensory
stimulations if we are curious that is
in the in the cases in which uncertainty
is such that we see uh the stimulus sort
of yields a promise of making sense if
we concentrate on it enough we will
probably uh um try to uh to put in place
epistemic actions there is actions uh
that we we perform in order to reduce
uncertainty and this could go from Cades
as we uh examine the picture uh up to
internet searches and every source of
actions aimed at reducing the ambiguity
or the uncertainty of our sensory
stimulations and if we are lucky enough
these epistemic actions leads us to
uncertainty reduction and in the end we
experience pleasure uh you may have
noticed you will have notice that when
you found the cow in the picture as with
uh many of these Mooney images you are
probably uh felt a positive affective
reactions that psychologists normally
call an AA moment or an AA experience
that has both cognitive and effective
components and and that accompanies the
increase the the sudden uh clarity about
the causes of your sensory
stimulation so overall this experience
generates a sort of Arc as we as we said
that goes from
uncertainty uh to pleasure and uh it is
an arc this is import it is important to
stress that this is an idolized
experience because things could go wrong
in many ways for example uh uncertainty
in your sensory stimulation could be so
high that you are not quite sure that
you can reduce it and so you don't
experience curiosity in the first place
because you don't are not confident in
the possibilities of reducing
uncertainty in your stimulations but it
could also be the case that your
epistemic actions do not lead to
uncertainty reduction but to an increase
in uncertainty instead after all it's a
changeable world uh and even if we put
in place actions to reduce uncertainty
it could be it could well be that uh
uncertainty
stays the same or increase even and
things could also go uh go wrong because
um uncertainty in some cases is not
reduced to an appreciable extent or is
not reduced fast enough for us to
experience this pleasurable effective
response so as I said this epistemic ha
is an idealized experience a way of
capturing successful sense making we
will say uh sense making that uptain in
an OP way but things could could go
wrong in many in many possible ways now
if we think about why we experience
pleasure while uh guessing the structure
of our sensorium while settling on a
specific hypothesis about the hidden
causes of our sensory data well that uh
has a pretty straightforward explanation
from a active inference perspective
because in this perspective as we know
reducing uncertainty is pleasurable
because it means maximizing model
evidence there is maximizing the
evidence for your own existence
something which how and others have
called self
evidencing but it's important to stress
and we stress in the paper uh that self-
evidencing is not to be seeing a sort of
passive process of confirming already
pre-existing uh belief but it's more
like an active process there is um it's
a process of self transformation as well
because in finding
the structure of our sensorium in
defining it in determining it we are
also determining the structure of
yourself as a model of that sensorium
and so finding structure is always
restructuring yourself in this way which
is a very active process and that will
be relevant in the in the in the rest of
our
discussion so reducing uncertainty is
pleasurable and these grounds several
theories of affect and wellbeing from a
predictive processing or active
inference perspective put some of the
papers relevant papers there U they all
more L stress that increasing prediction
error
or are normally effectively uh
negatively balanced whereas decreas in
prediction error are are normally seen
as
positive and uh these links well with
certain uh assumptions and certain
empirical results in the psychological
literature and in literature
in developmental robotic for example uh
it is known for example that infants
tend to concentrate on stimulations that
are neither too unpredictable nor too
predictable because these are the
stimulation that maximize their their
learning and their um the refining of
their model of the world this is known
as the goldilux effect and this sort of
environment these spaces of the of these
regions of the input space that afford
optimal and certainty
minimization are said sometimes called
progress niches and we'll see the
relevance for that for art in in a
minute so overall there is a view that
affect several aspect of our effective
responses are related to the Dynamics of
of uncertainty
minimizations and that we experience
positive effect uh uh in relation to our
successful attempts at uncertainty
iation and that this thing makes us
concentrate uh to into regions towards
regions of the input space that afford
such an optimal reduction in prediction
error
minimization now let's try to apply all
this to the case of
art
uh our contention in the paper that s
has been developing for some years now
um
is that art provides us with good
epistemic asss that is Art provides us
with these uh idealized experiences of
uncertainty minimization whereby we
start with something which is ambiguous
or not responding immediately responding
to our uh predictions uh then we uh this
thing has us to perform epistemic
actions that are in the end successful
and that leads to a pleasurable response
if we for example take this painting by
Monet we see this process going on at
sort of high low level perceptual level
which is um that the the ships and the
water here appears so vividly because we
uh probably puts in place the same thing
the same process that we put in place in
the case of the cow that is we have some
ambiguous simulations something which
not conform to the way in which normally
water or or or ships look to
but if we guess hard enough we are able
to see water and ships and then we get
this AA moment uh this pleasurable
effective response so what Monet is
doing here at a low perceptual level is
building such an idaliz form of
epistemic AR but of course that's
another important point is that these
epistemic ARS can go on at different
levels of obstructions and here we can
exploit the sort of hierarchical
structure the active inference and and
predictive processing insist on uh for
example in certain paintings like this
uh Yan Van painting here uh the matter
is not guessing what figures are in the
painting because these are represented
realistically but the the point is to
guess uh the meaning of the various
attitudes the various characters in the
picture or the various elements that
that uh that uh that the the painter
represent sense and their specific um
position in the painting as well so
these are higher level guesses uh which
if successful lead to the same circle
from uncertainty to pleasure that we saw
on a perceptual level in the Monet
painting and of course these guesses are
not just happening at different levels
uh but they are also different kinds for
example uh in in in case for example of
expressionist art uh the matter is not
just to guess the meaning of the
painting or the objects represented in
it but to a larger extent to guess the
intentions the state of Minds uh that
the painter uh was experiencing or had
while
depicting uh uh himself in this case or
any subjects uh uh and this is a form of
guess ing of other mental uh states that
is of course uh very important in the
predictive processing literature and
which uh Express expressionist that in
particular leverage a lot but other
guesses can have to do for example with
the sort of movements that are implied
or were put in place by the painter in
order to produce the painting we have an
example of the Famous Cuts By Lucha
Fontana here but you can also think
about the thick brush Strokes by Van
goog for example these allow these sort
of artworks allow the viewer the viewers
to uh make uh guesses about the actions
that went into the production of the
artwork itself so as you see the
predictive processing active inference
apparatus uh if leveraged to the full
extent of its possibility can account
for the pleasure that we get from
different art Works in different styles
in different moments in time as
well now it's also important to to to
understand then these guesses at various
levels
inform uh the guesses at the others
level for example if you um if you have
understood more or less the what figures
are in the
painting and you're making high level
hypothesis about their meaning and and
you and you make an high level
hypothesis about something in particular
you might be uh um pushed towards
reexamining certain portions of the
painting and noticing something on a
perceptual level that you didn't notice
before so often enough solving
ambiguities or uncertainties at a lower
level opens up problems on a higher
level and solving problems on a higher
level reopens problem on a perceptual
level and this in successful Arts goes
on and on and on and prolongs our
engagement with the artwork
itself importantly also artworks uh
great artworks in particular are such
that they keep us guessing uh they have
a good supply of structural
indeterminancy as uh Yuri lotman puts it
there is they are uh ambiguous in many
ways and such that if if you solve the
ambiguities the first time that you see
it uh you experience certain epistemic
acts if you revisit it you may
experience others epistemic act that you
hadn't considered before and you can uh
even uh experience more pleasure as a
result uh but indeed uh great hards are
seen as those sorts of inexhaustible
stimulations that keep providing us with
with uh important insights and that
might be a way of characterizing how
they do so in some if we take into
account all all these ways in which uh
art keep us guessing we will see that
artworks are conceivable interpretable
as hyper structural sensory
streams um progress niches in their own
right that allow us to keep uh improving
our models of the world in very refined
way and perhaps then the attraction that
we have towards these stimulations is
just part of a broader attraction that
we talked before for regions of our
input space that allows our optimal uh
cognitive
functioning now uh in this picture it is
important to stress that aesthetic
experiences are subjective in the sense
that whether a specific sensory array
will afford a pleasurable experience for
a specific agent will depend on the
generative model that it commands what
is unpredictable or ambiguous or or
uncertain for me can be perfectly
predictable for you and so uh if that's
the case it doesn't prompt the same
epistemic AR that it prompts for me uh
and we see these constantly uh in the
development of the individual and
Collective taste that often demands that
we uh search for more ambiguous more
unpredictable simulations as we learn
more about a specific art form in order
for us to recover the sense of wonder
and and and insight that certain
particular simulation with the right
kind of ambiguity gives us uh in this
picture aesthetic experiences are also
transient and evolving in the sense that
they depend on the specific dynamics of
uncertainty reduction and epistemic ARS
involved
um so for example for me this this Mony
painting if seen many many times won't
probably cause the same feeling of
insight and pleasure that it caused the
first time when I when I guessed the
presence of the ships and the water in
the painting much like uh seeing the cow
for the second time the cow that you saw
before uh doesn't prompt the same aha
experience to the same extent because
now you are more likely to directly
interpret it as a cow in an automatic
way and so you see that uh aesthetic
experiences are even with the same
stimulus can be very transient and
evolving and in a sense uh we are always
trying with aesthetic stimulations to un
to recover the sort of Ingenuity and and
uh that we had while seeing the picture
or the stimulation for the first time
and art is often characterized as
providing us occasions to see things as
for the first time and that could be a
way in which it does
so now the last thing I I will say about
um aesthetic experience in from this um
active inference perspective is uh that
as we saw aesthetic experiences are
often characterized as having something
to do with freedom of enhanced or
enhanced uh sense of agency for example
K talks about the free play of cognitive
faculties that will be involved in the
perception of a of a beautiful
object uh Shila even goes as far as
saying that it is only through beauty
that make makes his way to Freedom so
there is an ancient philosophical view
that links aesthetic appreciation
aesthetic
experiences uh to freedom from existing
constraints and an perception of our
possibilities for Action how do we
explain that from an active inference
perspectives well there are several ways
of accounting for that aspect of our
aesthetic experience one is that if the
the the picture that we gave so far is
right uh aesthetic experience are
occasion of enhanced self structuring in
the sense that they are moment where we
determine the structure of our sensorium
at a faster rate than usual and in doing
so we determine our own structure in a
faster rate than usual in a sense we
keep building ourselves we keep uh
changing uh we free oursel from existing
uh ways of perceiving things and we turn
our minds into moving targets uh while
we engage with these stimulations so uh
these probably captur something about
the notion of autonomy that can't had in
mind also when speaking about arts and
that is intriguingly finding new
application in cognitive science as well
and activist for example insist on this
notion of autonomy as well which is
giving yourself your own Rule and
perhaps in aesthetic experiences we are
doing that to an enhanced degree because
we are determining the structure of the
sensorium and the structure of ourselves
as models of that sensorium in a faster
rate at a faster rate than usual but
another way of thinking about how
aesthetic experiences can boost our
sense of Freedom an agency is that these
experiences are normally uh conducted uh
or encountered in the absence of
pressing needs that is we have no
pressing needs that push us to organize
our sensorium in precise ways and we are
free to explore many hypothesis about
the underlying structure of our
stimulations and this is probably what
people in Aesthetics uh uh talk about
when they talk about the aesthetic
disinterestedness there is that specific
state of mind that one has to have When
approaching something aesthetically
which is an a state of mind a mind of
Disconnect with practical interest or
interest of of other kind and this free
up space to explore other possibilities
of perceptual and cognitive
organization another thing that one can
take from the active inference uh
framework uh in order to explain this
relationship between aesthetic uh
experience and freedom is that uh
perhaps as we speculate in the
paper uh when we experience a sudden
reduction in prediction in in
uncertainty these in a c in in a certain
sense boost our confidence in the
ability to reduce uncertainty in the
future there are interesting uh Studies
by you and colleagues for example our
Barbarian colleagues that show in this
case for example that um even an AA
experience of the kind that you
experience with a cow can um encourage
risky decision making in in uh in in a
in a in a subsequent task and this study
by barbar and colleagues shows that the
stimulate that we tend to uh like uh are
also accompanied or Foster uh more
curiosity so in a sense one can can see
successful aesthetic experiences as
something that allows us to um broaden
that epistemic H That We examined before
uh and because we have more confidence
that we will be able if we engage with
epistemic actions for subsequent for for
for uh for the necessary time to reduce
uncertainty and we all face experiences
in which these epistemic ARS are very
short uh in the in the paper we do we
make the example of internet memes which
afford this very short epistemic Act of
of uncertainty and Discovery but art is
normally seen as boosting our confidence
in our ability to endurance and and and
uh uncertainty something which is
sometimes uh referred as negative
capability and and so that's perhaps
enough an interesting effect that art
could have if examined from this uh
active inference
perspective now summing up this part of
the of the talk we have seen that the
active inference of predictive protic
apparatus helps us explain why aesthetic
experiences are pleasurable namely
because they are instances of successful
self-
evidencing uh because they are sustain
why they are sustain self sustaining
because they are made of uh they may
they are made possible by sensory
streams that fuel our curiosity and keep
us guessing they are transformative
because they are instances of anoun self
structuring they are subjective because
they depend on the agent specific
generative model they are transient and
evolving because they depend on the
specific dynamics of uncertainty
reduction and they are linked to free
freedom and announced agency because
they are instances of announced self
structuring again conducting in the
absence of pressing needs and that boost
our confidence that as uncertainty minim
minimizes now for the second part of the
talk which is slightly
shorter uh we will examining ways in
which our mental functioning can be
illuminated by the Arts and Aesthetics
if we consider them from this predictive
processing
perspective now it's important to see
that in this framework artists uh are
seen as experts in cognition and in
inference in particular in the sense
that they know what cues ought to be
presenting to our sensory organs for us
to formulate certain evolving hypothesis
about what we are
sensing um a painter for example knows
what sensory array to produce in order
for you to guess that there is a certain
object in the painting but not just that
in order for you to guess it with a
certain profile of uncertainty
minimization and artist have a sort of
implicit largely implicit knowledge of
these dynamics of uncertainty
minimization for example they can feel
the tensions the visual tensions of an
imbalanced picture they can tell what
notes or what word are we expect uh uh
in a in a in a sentence or in a melody
and they can craft cinematic flows with
the right kind of abruptness or uh
invisibility
in in the editing for example so every
artist has in this framework sort of
large a large body of implicit knowledge
about the Dynamics of
inference and indeed art is probably a
place where these dynamics of inference
and their cognitive and affective
correlates become particularly visible
in the sense that all the what artists
are doing is to manipulate these
Dynamics in order uh to produce on us
cognitive and effective
reactions so therefore the thesis is
that artists and aestheticians to the
extent that they have access to this
large body of implicit knowledge might
therefore contribute to our
understanding of a mod things the
Dynamics of inference the Dynamics of
affect and certain aspect of wellbeing
and psychopathology so let's let's
examine these three things in
turn well as we said probably artist
assess this implicit understanding of
our inferential Dynamics for example if
the Moz here crafts a Melody he knows
whether certain note is to be expected
given the preceding context or whether
to introduce another note which is not
expected given the predictive context in
order to generate certain effects in
fact some people characterize uh music
theory as the most developed psychology
folk psychology currently extent exactly
to capture this fact that in within
artistic practice there is embedded a
large body of knowledge about our
Dynamic the Dynamics of our
inferences uh and the same goes for a
poet for example this is not a
particularly poetic example but for a
poet that chooses the carefully the
words the words of of his poem in order
to generate certain profiles of
uncertainty
minimization so one can say that artists
are stute manipulations of the inference
uh we make and the timing with which we
make them and this knowledge can indeed
be exploited to link the personal the
subpersonal level uh when we examine
experience for example and this is an
interesting point many of these
violation of our melodic or semantic
expectations have neural markers that
can be register with
electroencephalography as you see here
in the picture and so by linking these
uh neural correlates with the the
phenomenological variations that they
are accompanied uh by which artist and
aestheticians examine perhaps we can
have a a means to contribute the
literature on the Neal correlates of
Consciousness or to that um scientific
Enterprise that goes under by the name
of neurophenomenology that does exactly
this oper operation of connecting sub
personal and person level experience so
ad could give us access to ways of doing
that now as we said from a predictive
processing or active influence
perspective cognition and perception are
always accompanied by
affect uh because they are about uh our
existence as viable models of the world
so in mastering the Dynamics of
inference uh
artists are probably also mastering the
the Dynamics of affect and particularly
the Dynamics of those uh emotions or
those affective states that are
sometimes called epistemic or
metacognitive emotions things like
surprise confusion curiosity uncertainty
botom Insight this fluency and so on
many of these things interestingly are
are starting to be examined from a
predictive processing perspective and
and again art could be a way in which we
bring uh the expertise of artists and
aestheticians about these these states
and the way they are produced uh to bear
on Research in cognitive science that
examine the same thing and this could
also exam inform debates in philosophy
and cognitive science about things like
affective engineering affective
scaffolding anded extended effectivity
there is ways of
conceptualizing the many ways in which
we we um modify our effective states by
modifying things in the
environment and we manage our effective
states by uh managing the sort of
simulation that we encounter art seems
to be a particularly interesting case of
effective scaffolding or extended
effectivity and it is interesting to to
to to see that indeed art is starting to
be examined from that perspective in
some recent work as
well and finally as for well-being and
copathology well we saw that aesthetic
experiences if we are right have a lot
to do with optimal cognitive functioning
in the sense that they afford those
optimal um experiences that we
characterized as epistemic
CS uh they are about optimal information
seeking about optimal development of our
mental models and so to the extent the
that artists and aestheticians have
access to these Dynamics perhaps we can
gather for them indication on how to
design experiences that favor
involvement motivation learning and
Discovery and this is indeed an
increasing stream of research uh that
goes sometimes under the name of art
therapy um and there are many studies
examining the effects of the exposure to
Artistic stimuli on several cognitive fa
faculties and and abilities that seems
to go in that direction in the direction
of suggesting that artist has some sort
of knowledge on how to arrange sensory
streams that boost these things
involvement motivation learning and
Discovery and
finally uh
perhaps if aesthetic experiences have a
lot to do with optimal cognitive
functioning they can perhaps shed light
on on on forms of uh path pathological
cognitive functioning uh or epistemic
Behavior Uh
um because indeed one thing that active
inference allows us to do is to
conceptualize many pathologies of our
information seeking Collective
information seeking like Echo Chambers
conspiracy theories and so on and many
psychopathologies like schizophrenia
delusion autism anxiet and mood
disorders like anxiety and depression is
having to do something with suboptimal
ways of engaging with Environmental
uncertainty so if art can tell us
something about optimal cognitive
function perhaps it can tell us
something about deviations from the this
optimal cognitive functioning which it
is important to stress are often put in
place in order to recover that viability
in the end and and on the other hand
studies about uh uh these pathological
conditions could also inform the
production uh the study on the of the
production of Art and and aesthetic
experiences
um because as you know there is a long
tradition of uh of studies linking
creativity in in act with
psychopathological conditions for
example okay so let's draw some
conclusion now now and some direction
for future
research uh by just revers rehearsing
what we said so far uh so we we have
seen that there is a remarkable
convergence of interest and results
between scholar working within the
predictive processing or active
inference framework and Scholars
studying the Arts and Aesthetics this
convergence is proving beneficial for
both sides because on the one hand
predictive processing and an active
inference are Illuminating aspects of
our aesthetic
experiences things like why they are
pleasurable why they are self-
sustaining transformative subjective
transient and linked to freedom and
anoun agency uh apologies for the the
misspell
and on the other hand art and Aesthetics
are beginning to be seen as Windows into
mental functioning and revealing
something about the Dynamics of
inference the Dynamics of affet and
well-being and
psychopathology now to point out to
direction for future research uh in
Aesthetics in particular which is a big
field that has uh contributors from
philosophy psychology uh neuroscience
and so on uh the next thing to to study
probably from this predictive processing
or active inference perspective or the
next thing that are needed
are a more empirical testing of the
predictive processing hypothesis which
are sometimes very difficult to test in
in the in the in the introduction to the
theme issue we examine some of these
difficulties which have to do with the
mainly with the way of uh um Gathering
measures of uncertainty and uncertainty
minimization for example uh so more
empirical testing is needed but also
more insights into the neural
underpinnings of these Dynamics uh which
are quite often linked to the limic
systems and and the relationship between
uh the way in which we conceptualize
dopamine and other hormon from a
predictive processing perspective but
the neural underpinings of this
epistemic as these aha moments are still
all to be
clarified uh
also it is important to understand how
these predictive processing perspective
that we are advancing connects with uh
links to other Frameworks in empirical
Aesthetics which is a big field with a
long history H and this is particularly
important if you want to to
discern uh the specific predictions that
have to do with the predictive
processing framework from predictions uh
that are made in other Frameworks as
well and and important also expansion
expansion of the story would be its
extension to not just exteroceptive
stimulation uh which have been the
subject of our attention in the
presentation and in our papers mostly uh
that is stimulation that we get from the
environment but also propioceptive and
interceptive uh stimulations that have
also their own inferential Dynamics and
they could open possibilities is for
example to conceptualize also things
like sports performative Arts the
playing of instruments for example or
skillful motor Behavior as a way of as
as as a form of aesthetic experience
itself and another relevant expansion of
the story which hasn't been covered so
far a lot is taking the artist
perspective because we we talked a lot
about aesthetic exper
there is experience of subjects exposed
to aesthetic
stimulations but we haven't talked much
about uh the way in which these
stimulation are produced that is the the
creative the creative process that uh
it's put in place by artists in order to
generate these care carefully curated
sensory streams and there is a very
interesting beginning of that uh of
that exploration in the paper by by by
by Axel costant and colleagues in the
theme issue which I recommend uh I refer
you for more on creativity and and
active
influence more
broadly um the expansions of the view
that we that I am presenting for
cognitive science have to do as we said
already with uh studying the Dynamics of
inference after and what being in
Psychopathology which are all directions
that are very much still to be explored
but also there are many other phenomena
that are normally examined under an
aesthetic perspective but they that have
also been uh given accounts from a
predictive processing perspective things
like learning attention motivation and
conscious experience that are very much
still to be examined uh from this
perspective and the need and that will
probably profit from the encounter
between Aesthetics and and art on the
one hand and active inference on the
other okay I conclude by just uh
reminding you again of the theme issue
on these topics and thanking once more
my uh collaborators uh first of all sand
van C uh which is also here will be able
to um to to to to stay for the Q&A and
answer your concerns as well car friston
Helmut Le and
atico thank you very much for your
attention I look forward to an
interesting
discussion thank you thanks for the
presentation
awesome thank
you all
right
well lots of places to jump in perhaps
sander first and then Axel if you would
like to make any initial remarks or just
give any context or what you are left
with from the presentation
uh well it was a great overview of uh of
the work we've done together and um I
have little to add immediately um but
but yeah I need I'm I'm interested in
like how can we emperically test this
and how can we quantify uncertainty in a
way that um we can link it to people's
experiences uh and and in music This is
this is happening a bit like people are
using um models that output measures of
uncertainty
while uh while processing progressions
of ports for example uh this the work of
of Chun um and and there it's found that
these models the surprise measures and
the uncertainty measures that are
derived from from these models they uh
predict the emotions that that
individuals are are experien when when
listening to this music um so that so
that's an
interesting um an interesting step and
and next step I guess I guess would be
to look at it at a more more
personalized way in in in which we for
example have Jazz lovers and we we we
train this this computational model on
jazz music and and we see whether the
surpris the uncertainty that that kind
of model output that that it it relinks
better to the emotions of the Jazz uh
lovers uh than to General uh listeners
so so then it's really tuning the
uncertainty to to the to the individual
or or the group in this in this case so
that that's for me a very promising and
interesting um route to take next uh but
but in general I think I'm I'm happy
with with the story that jaoo told so I
I want to hear your
reactions great
Axel yeah well thanks ja for for talk it
was um really
interesting um so yeah I guess I have
two large sets of questions um uh one of
which you already sort of um highlighted
which is about creativity right relation
between the creativity as um the the you
know creativity as that which as an
attribute of the artist um product or
process and that's how you sort of
operationalize it uh in Psychology uh
sometimes uh you will have the
creativity of the thing that you sort of
uh produce that is a creative product or
a creative process and that is my my
experience as someone who who produced
that thing that is creative you know
that can also be creative in a sense
right um and um the first well the set
of questions that have to do with
creativity for me it's especially this
interesting observation that um the
creativity of the process doesn't seem
to be predictive of the creativity of
the product right uh because product
creativity you have like two criteria
the aptness and the novelty right and
the aptness has to do with uh let's say
I want to create a um a a stand for a
laptop it can be a creative laptop stand
uh but uh for that um stand to be uh
creative uh as a product quote quote um
it also has to work also has to hold my
laptop right so that's the appness
Criterion has to be useful and has to
work for what um it designed it's
designed to to do right and then you
have the novelty which is a statistical
Criterion which is from the point of
view of all the kind of laptop stands
that have been produced uh which of
those are considered you know most
original if you will from the point of
view of the people would assess all the
population of laptop stands right um and
again that doesn't seem to track with um
my creativity the creativity of the
process of me producing laptop stands
right so I can I I can think or feel
like I'm producing a pretty boring
laptop stand and it turns out to be a
very creative product creative laptop
stand right so I would be interested in
uh hearing you on the the sort of um you
know not a contradiction but something
that is slightly unexpected right um so
that's the first set of questions
concerning creativity it revolves around
this um finding interesting finding and
then the other set of questions um has
to do with and I think this is a more
General problem in the predictive
processing literature uh and aesthetic
aesthetic experience um we often say
that for you it's the concept of the
aesthetic Arc right and hearing hearing
you it it um it sounds as though um
traveling on the arc if you will so
reducing my uncertainty would in and of
itself be pleasurable right and I'm not
very clear on why that would be the case
I I I would like that to be the case
because it it sound very intuitive right
when I reduce my uncertainty it's like
it's a you know it's it's it's good it's
I like that it works well right but
really for that to be the case uh there
would be uh we would need kind of a
story about how how um
computational neuro uh computational
physiology according to active inference
right maps on to the actual physi
neurophysiology of pleasure right so I'm
not sure we have that story or maybe we
do but I I haven't seen it right or the
the the alternative would be something
like um once I'm at the end of that sort
travel on that Arc right I ared at an
outcome which will be pleasurable or
reward and that works for me right but
the art in and of itself because it's
sort of it's a process of minimizing
uncertainty it would be there for
pleasurable I I I would need more um
explanation of why that would be the
case right so I guess yeah those are the
two sets of
questions thank you very excellent
questions uh I'll probably I'll start if
you don't mind asand and then you'll
probably add more especially perhaps
about the the second question as well
but in any case yes so um creativity
process creativity versus uh product
creativity uh I think the discrepancy
that you point out could be
characterized as thinking again about
the fact that people have different
gener command different generative
models and have uh for example this
could lead to different views about
what's a great way of arranging a
sensory array in order to produce uh
certain results uh an artist could feel
that especially if it has practiced
similar procedures all all over all very
frequently that the solution at which he
he arri he or she arrives at is boring
or
uninteresting
um and the audience may feel very
different uh for the fact that they the
generative model is different they don't
expect a particular solution uh perhaps
uh even it's often the case that this
the solution has been arrived at
serendipitously uh the the designer
hasn't accounted for certain uses or
certain way of reading the stimulation
that people find in the stimulation
themselves because they command
different generative models and and so
perhaps there are ways of accounting for
this discrepancy between product
creativity and and process creativity
but it's very interesting I I I've
always found interesting the way in
which product creativity is described as
you said as being as having to do with
OP both opness and Novelty because it
seems that these two things captur two
aspects of the story that we have been
telling uh novelty of course captured
the the sort of
uncertainty uh unpredictability of a
certain sensory ARR and the way which
you should interact with it whereas
upness capture the sort of the the end
of the the parable the when when you get
the insight and you get how all the the
the pieces should should to fit together
and and you need to have both in order
to have an aesthetic experience in our
account and in order to be creative so
perhaps there is the nice there is the
nice link here between the aesthetic
experience uh of a viewer and the
creative process the generated that
experience right so it would be like I
had this laptop stand that I look at it
and I'm like what's that and I I start
try to use that thing and then I figure
out that it is a laptop stand and that
whole process right um you know once I
figured out that it is a laptop stand
and it works well as a laptop stand
right the aptness Criterion is met uh
but I had to to get to that point I had
to go through a process of uncertainty
minimization because it was such an
original in novel
exactly because you notice upness more
in a sense if it comes into a Contex in
which you need to Discover it uh
otherwise you are just acting
automatically on an object that you
already know how to use you can perceive
the creativity or the the object even a
MAG is creative in a sense because it
affords a certain uh way of using it but
you need to recover in a sense that
creativity that past generations of
makers have put into that object which
is is not visible to you anymore in a
sense to so again you have a a sort of
relationship between U creative
processes and which looks create look or
do not look creative according to how
habituated we are to them and the
aesthetic experience as we conceptualize
it which has to do with uh stimulate
that are novel enough for us to notice
them and but not so novel that we we are
not able to use them anymore
just I would just add to that because
that's very important to to see like the
aesthetic experience also as a creative
act in a sense that this blurring of the
of the line between the Creator and the
perceiver uh is is is important in this
view that that every aesthetic
experience is is in a sense because of
this discovery aspect and and a creative
act as well um and and so the appness is
very much dependent
on yeah the models of of the of the
viewer are the models of the Creator but
I mean that that there is discrepancy
outside and inside that's like a a
logical thing to me um and of course as
much as the models overlap between these
the audience and and the artist and uh
then there will be agreed upon
creativity
um strength as it were of of the the
object but but it might come across as
very creative for one person but not not
at all for another person so yeah yeah
and it it you know you often hear stuff
like especially for things like
Contemporary Art right uh where people
will say I don't see the point I don't
see why that's interesting right uh
whereas for another person who might be
some somewhat of an expert in
contemporary art that person would see
how interesting a novel you know as a
product that piece of work is right so
it it sounds like um even though you you
can explain why a creative process does
not necessarily lead lead to a creative
product right but there must be some
kind of you know there has to be some
kind of um you know you know tracking or
correlation between the two models um
the model of the perceiver and the model
of the artist that has produced right
the product or the piece of work because
otherwise you fall into those situation
where people they just don't understand
what's going on right and then there's
no aesthetic pleasure or aesthetic
experience right so then the question is
you know is there a sweet spot of um
kind of mismatch between because that
would that would be exactly what
accounts for the possibility of an
aesthetic art right there must be some
kind of mismatch between um the model
the artist that produce the product and
the model the perceiver right that uh uh
that you know perceives the product and
because if there's no mismatch it would
just be like a clear communication like
a stop sign right uh the model of uh the
uh the government that produced the stop
sign matches perfectly your model of
what a stop sign is and so there isn't
really a sort of an aesthetic Arc to go
through to understand you know the
meaning of the stop sign right so the
question becomes what is the The Sweet
Spot basically in terms of mismatch
between uh the model of the artist and
the model of the perceiver right and
then maybe you can look at art history
and what what typically is the sort of
educational background of great artists
what kind of a typical experience they
had in their life and what kind of model
that could have led to and how
mismatched that type of model right is
with the model of population at a
certain time in history right so uh yeah
yeah and and it's I mean that it's also
like the culturally dominant model that
is important there and and you see that
artists will play around and will hit
and miss in these kind of things I mean
they will experiment a lot uh and and be
uh be be uh early on their on their own
times like like they they they might um
propose like some some forms of
uncertainty that culture cannot deal
with at that time and a lot of the those
things we we just don't know about of
course because because they're not
filtered by history it's only afterwards
that we we realize like these Dynamics
we're playing we're playing and and he
found the The Sweet Spot but but uh yeah
it's it's not in advance I guess or or
very hard in advance
to uh to
[Music]
predict yeah I would add that there is a
whole field like in aesthetic theory on
in the theory of art which is call like
the Aesthetics of reception which whose
role is exactly to study the sort of
system of expectations that a certain
audience has at a certain moment in time
and the way in which the new artistic
product interacts with these
expectations uh by uh violating them um
to a larger or lesser extent and and and
so there is already a tradition of
studies that uh understood that if you V
at things too much the reception is not
going to be good if you violate them uh
too little it's not going to be
interesting so this the sort of Sweet
Spot talk that you that you adopted is
very much used in that literature as
well and of course this active inference
story has the merits of uh connecting
those early intuitions with this
neurocomputational language and and all
the literature on all the other
cognitive pH phoma that I explained
within the same framework I'd
say and as for the second also very
interesting uh um
question uh if I understood you well you
gave two Alternatives either you have
pleasure within the all uh along the all
ha that we have described or you have
pleasure in the end uh
right or to explain the relation between
pleasure and E estimate art would it
would be to say well there's kind of a
there's a process theory of active
inference right so it speaks also to
actual neurophysiology whether that
theory holds that's a you know that's an
open question but you know for the claim
to work that computational uh uh
neurophysiology would have to match the
neurophysiology of pleasure right I
don't know if that's the case or the
alternative is well it's not about the
arc it's about the end product and the
arc is what you need to get to the end
product right so yeah
yeah it's very interesting I agree uh
and that's one of the problem that I was
hinting at and in the end that there is
no clear story to my knowledge but my
knowledge is very limited because I have
a philosophic I'm philosopher by
training um about how to map these
things into the what is known about the
neurophysiology of pleasure the um the
limic system there there is some some
work in that direction uh we we
mentioned some of it in in the in the
paper that has to do with dopam
dopaminergic
discharge during the moment I guess so
in the end that would be in the end of
the process uh um but conceptually at
least what sustains the attention of the
viewer throughout the process is first
of all curiosity is not pleasure or not
pleasure in a traditional sense but the
expectation that things are going to uh
make sense in the end if we take enough
effort to make to to observe them and
and the other half is the the pleasure
half I would say in which uncertainty if
you are lucky gets reduced and gives you
this output but yeah I'm curious to to
to to to see what what sand thinks about
the question as
well yeah I'm
not I think uh if you talk about
neurophysiology of course active
inference has a a whole other take on
the dopamin arch system and and all all
these reward systems but but but
um in a sense I I think the the positive
effect is just um like you talked about
this confidence boost after
restructuring after sudden restructuring
I think the the the positive effect is
just this feeling of the confidence and
the opening up of of
Alternatives which probably has to do
with with kind of um
a a Precision that
is um yeah in a diffuse way um
projecting back to to all the things
that you you are doing but but in what
way specifically that that's that's very
unclear to me like but it seems to be
that dopamine dopamine might be well
placed or these systems might be well
placed to have a diffuse effect on
further processing in a kind of
uh yeah uh
energizing
sense but but but I'm not thinking about
pleasure as the traditional reward sense
uh I don't I don't think that's very
useful in in a in a netive
inference uh framing um yeah because
yeah it it doesn't really explain much
if you yeah if if you just point to a
reward center that is then activated and
so so so I I I try to see it as more as
as a kind of network effect and a kind
of um yeah as you discussed this sub
subsequent effects of of an AA that then
um boost your your your autonomy by by
having these effects on on Precision uh
but yeah that's all very speculative
still I
think yeah um so so two points Jack you
said um having a sustained attention
right so maybe in what we call aesthetic
experience there there needs to be
sufficient sufficiently sustained
attention for at Le for long enough to
get to that sort of rewarding but not
rewarding point but that end point uh
Center that you're talking about right
so maybe that's the the you know the the
ep the epistemic aspect of that Arc um
it its function would be to maintain the
say attention for long enough and now
the question is you know what what what
does that afford to to that experience
is and then an answer could be something
like uh there's research on how in those
models the volatility in your beliefs
about the structure of the world that is
your transition Matrix that relate to
stuff like anxiety right from the point
of view of neurophysiology right so
maybe that what we call aesthetic
pleasure is just the release uh or the
you know the reduction of a feeling of
anxiety and uncertainty right and the a
moment it's not like a um a of knowledge
it's a a of relief right so it's U I
don't know maybe maybe that's how you
can conciliate the but at any rate you
would have to make um or people who make
that claim that the arc is pleasurable
because reducing uncertainty is
pleasurable I again I'm not and I know
Senator that's not that's not your claim
but I feel like that in the literature
we we sometimes read that minimizing the
uncertainty per se is
pleasurable I doubt that that's the case
maybe has that is you know reduce
anxiety makes you in a you know you know
in in a in a state that you're poised to
you know having the sort of pleasurable
endpoint or something like that yeah
that's an important point that that that
maybe wasn't emphasized enough but
indeed like if if if active inference is
true then we're constantly reducing
uncertainty by actions by walking and so
it cannot be merely that it has to to do
with some kind of unexpected rate of of
of uncertainty reduction so so they have
have to be that's why artists work with
with obstacles and and and and in
creating uncertainty to to yeah to try
to have us this experience um but always
in a in a like a fallible way of course
but to try to give us the experience
that that we s ly resolve the
uncertainty in a way that is faster than
than we expected maybe when engaging
with it
first yeah but that that's just that
just sort of pushes the problem upward
right it's not this first level of
uncertainty and the sort of it's the
uncertainty over the uncertainty but you
know if you say well that's you know the
pleasure comes from reducing the
uncertainty over the uncertainty you
haven't solved the problem right you
just sort of further push it upward in
the hierarchy basically um I guess the
problem is that we don't have a good
story of why um reducing uncertainty per
se would be tied to like pleasurable
experience
right um and and what what what what
would what would you find like a a um a
kind of
satisfying explanation because for me
it's not so much that
like it it it seems
like um this it is more puzzling to me
to start from a rewards perspective
where you people get rewarded by some
things uh Suddenly by having some
activity and reward
structures um the the advantage of this
story is that that it's not it's not
about the reward but it's about this
engagement with the environment that
that is uh positively or negatively
balanced depending on how how well we
are doing in in this uh structuring or
predicting it uh so
so
so yeah I guess I guess maybe your your
question is then like what is still the
function of the positive experience uh
do we need it at all if it's um can it
be just an epic phenomenon or something
uh and that's a fair questions question
but but but uh yeah I think that we have
to look at the the consequences of the
positive effective experience and and
and not so much yeah at I don't
know um I does that does that make sense
to you
to that kind of uh or what's your
question about the the the the
phenomenology of of of effect or right I
mean I I would have I could respond
something but I maybe then there there
are people that have uh questions in the
chat or do you want to I think there's
like 14 minutes left or so so if you
wantan
to I think this points to some of the
the very complex and interwoven aspects
of the art viewing experience and
separating out like primary sensory
reductions of uncertainty then there's
art pieces that leave us with questions
so then okay well then that is
increasing our Precision on us being the
kind of cultural thing that's left with
a question after the Shakespeare play
those start getting into very
stacked and and socially enacted kinds
of uncertainties and actions and
Pleasures that may be very distal from
the laptop stand it could be like like
oh it's it's giving me a feeling like
there was care in the production of the
artifact or I know the person who made
it so then the eye that the parent
brings to the child's art piece is
different than the art reviewer for an
art
show and so it's um almost like an
invitation to explore those alternative
hypotheses now within a space where we
can at least jux depose them and
recombine them because there's so many
media
specific and and experiential elements
that can't necessarily
be separated out very
cleanly because we're talking about the
human reception of art not a um insect's
reception of two solid colors something
that that might be more
isolatable to elements like ambiguity or
luminance or more basic properties of
the
stimuli and then I think the one the
example you showed with a torn
canvas how that's a trace left by a
process um and then the stop sign
too I mean in a way modern art has kind
of broken Bren that that fourth wall
with the urinal and with the with the
blank squares and all these kinds of
things that that
complexify just the day-to-day
engagement and for some people there
it's a
bizarre um unnecessary
complexification for other people it's
kind of a
re-enchantment with regular
objects and it just shows
how even an object that somebody did not
intend to produce as art could still
trigger a deeply aesthetic
experience and so it's almost
like more questions than answers
perhaps nice
yeah I mean yes one of the advantages of
the story we have been presenting I
think is that active inference offers is
this
possibility to exploit the
hierarchical organization of our
predictions
uh of course as predictions becomes more
abstract and are also more difficult to
to test and to to verify and we enters
into a a lot of very difficult to to
pinpoint predictions uh which are
cultural in nature uh uh that that have
enough effect of our appreciation of of
a particular artwork but we are not
quite able to pin point but the idea is
that with for example with abstr art a
lot of the way in which they function as
aesthetic stimulations is by playing
with our very higher level expectations
about for example how an artwork would
look like according to a specific art
world according to a specific community
of art uh consumers and if Duan for
example could make art by by signing a
neuronal it is because he was playing
with these very high level expectations
about what art is supposed to look like
it's like a challenge it could be
conceptualized among other things as a
challenge to see that P specific object
as an artwork in the same way in which I
I suggested that a particular sensory
array could be seen as a cow so if you
manage to do so to see that specific
object an artwork you get thata insight
which is similar to that sort of low
level Insight that you got with the cow
but on a higher level and um yes so one
could exploit this hierarchical story in
order to account for different things
among among them uh abstract art as well
there is a very interesting piece on
abstract art in the theme issue by a
heart historian ladisl kesna uh so that
would be another thing to look uh into
for example
yeah yeah one one comment from the live
chat Holly wrote when thinking about
abstract painting the viewer might find
pleasure in compositional elements like
variety contrast repetition unity and
balance in addition to the
interpretation and
gesture yeah sure I mean uh of course
there are also these uh these uh things
about the arrangement of of of elements
in in the canva the way in which they
they create a balanced or unbalanced
design how we explain the the the the
intentions of the painter to position
these elements in this particular way of
course if we know more about this
particular poetic of that artist if you
for example it becomes vital with
certain artists like mandrian or
Kandinsky to know also about the
theoretical writings in order to make
sense of why they are using certain
colors and certain shapes in certain
forms so it's also a case that with abst
art what is sometimes called the
the the broader context the epit text
all the things the information are
around the artwork gain more importance
because there are ways in which artists
set expectations on us not by things
that they put in the artwork themselves
but by
presenting them within a certain context
of theories and so on so the a lot of
predictions are installed by artist in
in abstract art in this epit text more
than in in the work
itself awesome if I quick can quickly
add on because this is a point I wanted
to raise is that um now we're talking
about aesthetic experience um I think
you can appreciate our outside of
aesthetic experience as you said ja so
you can appreciate let's say an artwork
as a art historical object and then you
have this sort of a intellectual
pleasure with it uh and even with you
when you look at uh let's say conceptual
Arts right uh there's this uh well um
what will happen often times is that
they will use this device called a
citation right whereas in the piece of
the artwork there will be a citation to
earlier work and you can appreciate the
citation if you know the art history
right so um but in that case you're kind
of outside I well and that's the beauty
of active inference are you really
outside of the domain of aesthetic
experience maybe you can make claim that
you're you're within the same sort of
regime of like computational processes
and ctive processes sure but um let's
say in the common sense of aesthetic
experience then your experience you know
relies much less on the sort of um
rolling uh you know sensory processing
Dynamics right that you would have in
something like I don't know um you were
mentioning um abstract and uh you know
Kandinsky and where you have a lot of
colors you have difficulties
interpreting the the the the figure and
so on and so forth right so um maybe it
would be useful to talk of different
aesthetic experience and for different
objects and different ways of
appreciating those objects and that
might help clarifying right that maybe
different um uh you know trajectories on
the epistemic arc right and so on and so
forth so all the kind of problems that
we discussed today maybe that be a good
starting point with us the tax on to me
like
that yeah I mean I don't know whether s
agrees but I think we are all always in
the same sort of aesthetic domain there
are no differences if not in this in
sort of abstractions in here the the
nature of predictions that you put uh
into play in the different cases between
appreciating something for it lowlevel
features and the way in which they are
combinable and having this very abstract
high level knowledge of the art scene
that informs your
guesses uh and your appreciation of
artworks also because these processes
and these guesses inform one another so
you need to have sort of plastic view of
where the bounding is or or not having
boundaries at all between these two
things uh because for example if you
know for example the title of Picasso
bullsh Head the thing sort of sculptur
for by pieces of a bicycle if you know
the title that's sort of a high level
information about the artwork uh we are
also inclined to concentrate on certain
sensory features of the object instead
of others and to make some lowlevel
inferences instead of others and if you
make those inference perhaps you
formulate new high level hypothesis and
these two things continuously inform one
another uh and that's the same process
to me as long as you have these
epistemic ARS that leads you towards
some sort of discovery which could be
high very high level or low level I mean
to me it's one of the advantages of the
framework I don't know whether sand
agrees or not yeah completely yeah I I
would even yeah make it more
broadly I mean the the even in games uh
you have these epistemic arcs and and
just in
everyday life they they might I mean
we we call them the like a minimal unit
of sense making and and it is it is kind
of that so it it's not really
necessarily attached to Art um but it is
a kind of uh pleasure that is not
derived from like uh food or or uh sex
or the the the kind of typical rewards
that people use in
Psychology um um so so so and and that's
the advantage of course of active
inference that it that it makes room for
this kind of like I would call it a
pleasure of obstacle clearing in in in a
general sense to towards what you want
instead of getting what you want it's
it's like we want to problem solve in
order to to get where we want and I
think it makes sense for for evolution
to to reward like this this obstacle
clearing and this this overcoming
challenges which is of of course
uncertainty so of overcoming uncertainty
is is the reward as such um and it makes
sense I think for evolution to to to
organize us as as such and maybe as as
humans more than than other animals but
you see them also like I I give the
example of my dog that that often picks
the the largest kind of unwieldy stick
to to play with and I see that happen
and I I I think it's probably because it
gives him the most Challenge and if it
gives him an obstacle to overcome and if
I don't want to play with him uh he has
to find his own obstacles and he has to
find ways to reduce uncertainty in
display uh that that that he generates
himself and and that's art as well of
course um so so yeah that's for me the
the the strength of the the approach in
active
inference yeah if I can add very brief
remark
um that that's in to some extent that's
going back to the sort of modern origin
of Aesthetics to Bard and who used to
think of Aesthetics as the science of
sensus sensus cognition he said in
general um so of course the difference
between everyday experience and
aesthetic experience will be that
aesthetic experiences or aesthetic
objects present ourselves with these
more
idealized form of uncertainty
minimization that we tended to
characterize with The epistemic Arc and
I I showed how things could go wrong in
many ways ideally in art when it when
when art works we get this epistemic us
in a very uh purified and idealized form
and that's what why these experiences
are more pleasurable but indeed the the
component the the inferential component
of that experience is something that we
find in experience more broadly because
as as all experience is finding
structure in our sensorium but not all
experience is as successful in in
finding structure in our sensorium as
aesthetic experiences
are awesome well in closing if you have
any last
thoughts or any short ideas or visions
for how the art stream series might
continue on its own epistemic
path so let's do yeah jacoba first then
sander and axel okay thank you um yes I
just hope that this were this was very
non-technical overview of the field I
just hope that it got people interested
in active inference in interested in
this work on Art and Aesthetics in
particular because uh I think it holds
lots of promises interesting
applications and I look forward to the
the rest of the this art stream that
this U first uh encounter inaugurates
and uh an obvious solution for me would
be to contact the authors of the theme
issue that I talked about uh but there
are also several people that are trying
to test this thing experimentally as
well in psychological or neuroscientific
labs and if you need any help in
contacting them or or in uh finding out
people uh for for for the art stream I'm
I'm here of
course thank you
CER yeah I second that I I think it
would be nice to uh to to try to work
towards um more empirical ideas and to
see what people have have done and how
how we can build on that um because yeah
that in in the end that
that's that's the promise of active
inference if it if it doesn't allow us
to get a better handle on like uh
uncertainty and quantifying uncertainty
relating it to the phenomenology during
art perception then there is I mean then
people might say it's just a rehearsal
of some class ideas about expectation
violation in art and so it's really like
the the kind of and also of course the
kind of AI models that we now have to to
to to uh use as a proxy for uncertainty
and surprise and to see whether that
captures something in Human Experience
uh if we if we start to use text or
music as I said uh so so yeah that's
really the the advantage of of the
approach and and the promise
um that we have to
show um to the field in general of of
Aesthetics and neuro
Aesthetics thank you Axel yeah and um I
fully agreed with all that um and maybe
having some artists uh invited that
would be very interesting uh because um
there's a lot of Applied uh active
inference theory if you will and but
most of the time it's applied to experts
that are like us right if you if you
have cogn and think in a normal way
active in Prince applies to you it
applies also to people who are experts
in certain domains um but you know for
the art it would be interesting to have
like expert artists and I think in a
special issue there's Robert pero is is
that right yeah which what he does is
super interesting and for the in a
couple of second the the the short story
is um that's one artist that I discussed
in my Mastery thesis that I did under
the supervision of sander actually so
it's interesting for me this whole you
know art stream because goes full circle
for me uh is started with uh the
aesthetic experience of well all like
experience and transformative experience
in productive processing right then move
to Evolution biology and then you know
Psychiatry and so on and so forth uh but
yeah so having invited artists that
would be cool and uh you know maybe
pursuing those other topics that in the
end all relate to aesthetic experience
um you know in biology and so on and so
forth you know yeah awesome I hope we
can do it if someone's listened this far
and they wna jump on for an art stream
or suggest something that would be great
so thank you fellows great to hear this
and till next
time
bye for